Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 12 -- Letters from Franklin 1733-1789 Mss.B.F85inventory12
American Philosophical Society
- Letters from Benjamin Franklin
  - to [Joseph] Galloway., 1774 September 7; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Great expectation of the result of the appointed Congress both among friends and enemies. If the Colonies declare and resolve their rights and confederate not to use British goods till they are acknowledge and confirmed, they will carry their point. The Ministry must be disbanded and the late Acts repealed. A war with Spain is apprehended.
  - to Peter Timothy., 1774 September 7; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    The success of the Congress depends upon the unanimity and firmness of its members. The Ministry must give way. Intends remaining in England another winter.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 131; Bigelow, V, 361; Smyth, VI, 243).
  - to [John] Foxcroft., 1774 September 7; A. Dr. L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    There is a good deal of uneasiness at the office concerning the delay of the accounts. Mr. [Anthony] Todd showed him a letter which he sent to Mr. [John] Foxcroft. Urges him to pay attention to the contents if he values the continuance of his appointment. Thinks Some person is ready to step into his shoes.
  - to [The Provincial Council of New Jersey]. Samuel Tucker, Jno. Mehelm, Robt. Friend Price, Henry Paxson and Ja[me]s Kinsey [Committee]., 1774 September 7; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    The Acts of the Assembly for which he is to obtain the Royal approbation. Hopes to receive copies of the Acts and also the votes. Unanimity and firmness in Congress will do everything for them. Will inform them of any measures that may affect the liberties of America. War with Spain apprehended.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VI, 242).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1774 September 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Has not received a line from her for the last nine months; censures her for not writing. Continues well and hopes to hear the same from her. Recommends Mr. Westley to her civilities.
  - to [The Provincial Council of New Jersey]. Samuel Tucker, Jno. Mehelm, Robt. Friend Price, Henry Paxson and Ja[me]s Kinsey [Committee]., 1774 October 12; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Officers of the Plantation Board as well as its members are out of town; nothing can be done in regard to the late Acts until their return. A dissolution [of Parliament] has taken place which was very sudden and unexpected. Cause for this dissolution.
  - to Jos[eph] Galloway., 1774 October 12; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Election of a new Parliament. Lord Percy's friends published a letter of his expressing that he is on good terms with the people of Boston. The Court persists in its severe measures against America. His situation in England hazardous.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 138; Bigelow, V, 370; Smyth, VI, 252).
  - Memorandum., [1774.]; A. Dr. of Diss.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    When we see how easily the Nation is moved by party writers and declaimers, how its mind is easily changed to purposes directly contrary by a pamphlet or a protest, how can we resolve to submit to its Government without check or without being represented. Will submit only when we can no longer resist.
  - True State of the Proceedings in the Parliament of Great Britain and in the Province of Massachusetts Bay., [1774.]; Diss. 12p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Relative to the giving and granting the money of the people of that Province, and all America in the House of Commons in which they are not represented.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IV, 466).
  - to The Printer of the Public Ledger., [1774.]; A. Dr. of L.S. "A Londoner." 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    On the causes of the existing bad feelings between England and America.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VI, 214).
  - to Thomas Cushing., 1775 January 28; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Lord Chatham's motion for conciliatory measures rejected. More troops sent to America. Petitions to restore the commerce with America are daily arriving. The Petition from the Congress was brought into each House without any particular recommendation from His Majesty that they should be considered. From one of General Gates's letters it appears that Lord Dartmouth advised him to disarm some of the Colonies by force.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 140; Bigelow, V, 426; Smyth, VI, 301).
  - to Dr. [Josiah] Tucker, Dean of Gloucester., 1775 February 10; A. Dr. of N.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Begs to be informed whether his of the 26th of Febryary, 1774, came to hand.
  - to [The Provincial Council of New Jersey, Samuel Tucker et al. Committe]., 1775 February 14; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    All their Acts of March last are likely to pass the Board of Trade except those for lowering the interest of money and for the relief of an insolvent debtor. Petitions are being received from all parts praying that commerce be restored. Both Houses have addressed the King declaring a rebellion to be in Massachusetts; more troops are about to be sent thither. A bill is preparing to deprive the four New England Colonies of their fisheries. Lord Chatham's plan for conciliation was rejected by the Lords.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VI, 307).
  - to [Joseph Galloway]., 1775 February 25; A. Dr. of L.S. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Plan of union sent by Galloway to England. It is hinted that Mr. Galloway and Mr. [John] Jay are friends of the Ministry, Dr. Franklin does not believe it. Objections to a union. Preliminary articles to be agreed upon before such a plan should be adopted. Lord North's proposal meant to divide rather than to unite the Colonies.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 144; Bigelow, V, 435; Smyth, VI, 311).
  - to The Earl of Darthmouth., 1775 [March 16.]; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Protests against the blockading of Boston harbor and the pending Acts for depriving that Province of fishing rights.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, V, 79; Bigelow, V, 529; Smyth, VI, 397).
  - to Mr. -----., 1775 March 17; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Is about to embark to America, and requests him to omit purchasing the Theatrum Machinarium if he had not already done so; has an offer of a set in London. Informs him that if he has purchased it, his draft will be paid by Mrs. [Margaret] Stevenson. Proposes to return in October. Presents his respects to the Prince.
  - to Mr. [Anthony] Todd., 1775 March 18; A. Dr. of L. in 3d P. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Sends extracts from letters from Mr. [John] Foxcroft to Dr. Franklin, to show what reason Dr. Franklin had to suppose the accounts might have been settled.
  - to D[avid] Hartley., 1775 May 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Arrived last night and learned that there is the most perfect unanimity throughout the Colonies. Introduces Capt. Falconer.
  - to Thomas Bradford., 1775 May 16; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Applies to Mr. Bradford in behalf of a clergyman who is supposed to have spoken some disrespectful words of him; claims they are greatly misrepresented; hopes he will find the offense not to require such marks of resentment as may be misconstrued in English.
    Printed in Works (smyth, VI, 402).
  - to The Earl of Chatham et al., [1775. May.] ?; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Thanks by The [Continental] Congress to the Earl of Chatham, Edmund Burke, David Hartley, and the Bishop of St. Asaph, for their efforts in behalf of America.
  - to William Temple Franklin, Amboy, N. J., 1775 June 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Advises the proper use of his youthful oppurtunities to get knowledge. Has sent part of his baggage to Amboy. Family news.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VI, 405).
  - to Mr. [John] Sargent., 1775 June 27; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Asks him to keep the money which will be given to him by Messrs. Brown and Collinson. Fears his Ameican property, which consists of houses in seaport towns, may be burnt by Great Britain. America will give England one more oppurtunity for recovering her affections and retaining the connection.
  - to Messrs. Brown and Collinson., 1775 June 27; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Requests them to pay the balance of his account to John Sargent whose receipt will be their discharge.
  - to Mrs. Margaret Stevenson., 1775 July 17; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Finds no convenience of putting out her money in America, and has concluded to return it. Sends an order for £260. Advises her what to do with her money.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VI, 411).
  - to [Joseph Priestley]., 1775 October 3; L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Sets out for the camp to-morrow. Asks him to tell Dr. [Richard] Price that America is determined and unanimous, and to calculate how long it will take the British to kill all the Americans and conquer their whole territory, from the statstics he gives.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VI, 429).
  - to [Charles Guillaume Frederick] Dumas., 1775 December 9; 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Sending £200 as compensation for his services and to defray the expenses of his mission. Promise that his services will always be recognized and rewarded by Congress.
  - to Destroy Civil Liberty., [1775.]; A. Dr. of Diss. 1p.; Efforts of France and England
  - Proposed Resolution of the Continental Congress., [1775 July 7]; A. Dr. of D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Since America aided Great Britain in conquering Canada and Louisana, and has not been given any consideration for it, resolved that, in case such satisfaction is refused, all lands in America claimed by the Crown and all quit rents unpaid to the same, shall be considered as liable to an appropriation for that purpose. Advise all persons not to pay quit rents and not to purchase lands from the Crown till such satisfaction shall be made.
  - Protest of the Representatives of the State of Pennsylvania Against the Proposed Inequality of the Votes in Congress, and Dissent to the Articles of Confederation for that Reason., [1776 July.]; A. Dr. of D. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Printed in Journals of the Continental Congress, Vol. V, 1776, p. 554, Note (Washington, 1906).
  - Proposed Resolution of the Continental Congress., [1775 on or before July 21]; A. Dr. of D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Draft of a motion to shut up all custom houses in the Colonies from and after July 20, 1776; to discharge the officers of the same, and to open all the ports to the ships of every state of Europe that will admit their commerce and protect it; resolve to support this freedom of commerce for two years and as long after as the late Acts of Parliament for restricting the commerce and fisheries shall continue unrepealed.
  - to Lord [Howe?]., 1776 August 20; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    The temper of the Colonies as professed in the several petitions was sincere; the terms they proposed should have been closed with and all might have been peace. The contempt with which the petitions were treated and the cruel measures since taken have changed that temper. To propose submission to the Crown would now be fruitless.
  - to Lord Howe., 1776 September 8; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Benjamin, Franklin, Philadelphia
    Cause for not answering sooner. Concerning an interview requested by his Lordship.
    Priinted in Works (Sparks, VIII, 187; Bigelow, VI, 30; Smyth, VI, 462).
  - to William Temple Franklin, Perth Amboy, N. J., 1776 September 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Benjamin, Franklin. Philadelphia
    Thinks it not advisable for him to go at this time to his father. Will send clothing by first oppurtunity. Attempt of Benny [Benjamin Franklin Bache] at letter-writing.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VI, 467).
  - to William Temple Franklin, Perth Amboy., 1776 September 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Benjamin, Franklin. Philadelphia
    Reasons for not wishing him to take the journey to his father.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VI, 468).
  - to William Temple Franklin, Perth Amboy., 1776 September 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Benjamin, Franklin. Philadelphia
    Has an advantageous offering for him if he returns immediately.
  - to [Juliana Ritchie.], 1777 January 19; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Paris
    His precaution against spies. The various conjectures concerning his business do not harm him; does not think it necessary that he should take the least pains to rectify them.
    Printed in Works (Bigelow, VI, 54; Smyth, VII, 11).
  - to The F[armers]-G[eneral]., [1777 Jan. 10-13]; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; The American Commissioners
    Cannot treat for all the tobacco that may arrive in France, as a great part will come on account of private merchants, to discharge debts. Whatever contracts they make concerning tobacco, in order to obtain immediate supplies for the armies of the Congress, will be executed. Considering the lowness of the price of tobacco, they do not think their proposal that the Farmers-General should be at a risk of transporting the goods, to be unreasonable. The English carried on the trade on the same conditions.
  - to The F[armers]-G[eneral]., [1777 Jan. 10-13]; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; The American Commissioners
    There is no place in which all the tobacco is collected for transportation. It is brought to the public magazines of the Inspectors for each District. Are willing that Congress shall procure receipts for 20,000 hogsheads of tobacco lodged in the magazines and that the ships of the Farmers-General may take it, as the British ships used to do. Price of the tobacco and the manner and condition on which they are to take it.
  - Agreement between the American Commissioners and [Col. Deshays De] la Radière., 1777 February 17; A. Dr. by Benjamin Franklin, of D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Paris
    Relative to his entering the service of the United States.
  - Memorandum., 1777 February 17; Dr. of D. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Agreement concerning the employment of Duportail, de Laumoy, and de Gouvion in the American service.
    (In English and French.)
  - to [The Farmers-General]., 1777 February 26; A. D. (by Franklin). 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    The American Commissioners cannot accept the price offered by the Farmers-General nor make any change in their last proposition.
    (In French.)
  - to M. Paulze, 1777 March 17; A. Dr. of L. (by Franklin). 2p.; The American Commissioners?, Passy
    Have consider the proposition of the Farmers-General. Are willing to agree to the articles proposed but with an additional proviso regarding the eventual cost of the tobacco to both parties.
  - Agreement between the American Commissioners and the Farmers-General., 1777 March 24; D.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Copy of contract or agreement between the American Commissioners and the Farmers-General, represented by M. Paulze, by which the former agree to purchase in the American Colonies and deliver to the Farmers-General in France a certain quantity of tobacco at a fixed price per pound to be paid by the Farmers-General.
    (In French. Copy.)
  - Memorandum., 1777 May 30; Mem. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Charleville
    Agreement between the American Commissioners and ----- Mercier with reference to the repairing of arms and weapons of warfare.
  - to Gen[eral] Washington., 1777 June 21; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Paris
    Introducing M. de Bretigny, Captain of Infantry, who brings nine officers to America at his own expense. Names of officers given.
  - to The Secretary of the Royal Medical Society of Paris., 1777 June; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Received the copies of the Charter and the tickets which he sent him in behalf of the Royal Society [of Medicine]. Is extremely sensible of the honor they did him in placing him at the head of their foreign members. Will not fail to attend the meeting of the 20th instant to which he is invited.
  - to The Ship "Harmony.", 1777 August 29; D.S. B[enjamin] Franklin, Silas Deane. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Paris
    Passport.
  - to The Ship "Capricieuse., 1777 August 29; Dr. of D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Paris
  - to Contract between the American Commissioners and Rey de Morande., 1777 October 31; D.S. Rey de Morande, B[enjamin] Franklin, Silas Deane, Arthur Lee. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    For the purchase and delivery in America of 180 cannon of various sizes, the purchase price to be paid in tobacco by the Continental Congress.
  - to [A.M. Hevin de] Navarre and [François Antoine,] Baron de seyffertit., 1777 December 4; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Has no authority from Congress to entertain officers for their service, except a few engineers and officers of the artillery who are long since gone. All others who have passed to America have gone at their own expense and contrary to his advice.
  - to M. Goudeman., 1774 December 10; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    M. [Antoine Félix] Wuibert one of his countrymen and as such may depend on the same care and pains to procure his liberty as for any other the most favored of our people; hundreds are in the same situation; England has rejected, with insolence, all proposals for exchange of prisoners.
  - A Dialogue between Britain, France, Spain, Holland, Saxony and America., [1777.]; A. [?]; Franklin, Benjamin
    A humorous paper relative to the political affairs of the several countires at the beginning of the American Revolution. 4 p.
    copy.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, V, 116; Bigelow, VI, 118; Smyth, VII, 82).
  - to M. Brillon., [1777 before Aug. 25]; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Asking for M. Hennet's address.
  - Cipher Code., [1777 Sept]; A. Dr. of D. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to Louis Le Bègue du Portail., [1777 Jan. 11]; Dr. of L. in 3d P. 1p.; The American Commissioners
    Gives the four conditions made by M. Duportail which the Commissioners grant.
  - to -----, -----., [1777.]; Dr. by Jean Baptiste Le Roy of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Is glad that so many brave soldiers in Europe have offered their services to his country. Thanks him for his intentions and is grateful for the verses sent.
  - to -----, -----., [1777.]; Dr. by Jean Baptiste Le Roy of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Would like to know French well enough to appreciate fully the merit of hs verses. Received from M. Brillon the gift he sent and thanks him for it.
  - to -----, -----., Dr. by Le Ray de Chaumont of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Congratulations on learing of his marriage. Regrets he cannot personally make their acquaintance.
  - to -----, -----., Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Acknowledging the author's beautiful poem, with the flattering mention of himself contained therein.
  - to -----, -----., [1777.]; Dr. by Jean Baptiste Le Roy of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Thanks for verses. Is not proficient enough in French to fully appreciate their worth, but is grateful for the sentiments expressed about his country and himself.
  - * Exercises in French., [1777.]; A. Dr. of Mem. 11p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Translation of a chapter from the Bible—Abraham and the stranger.
    * This is the "Tacable Against Persecution"
  - to M. Rolandeau., 1778 January 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Paris
    Can not otherwise give an order for his passage gratis than by giving an order to their correspondent to pay the money on Franklin's account, and that should not reasonably be expected. Thinks that as he left the service of the States without leave, he should bear the whole expense of the voyage.
  - to [Ralph] Izard., 1778 January 29; A.Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Until he can see him submits to remain under the opinion he has formed not only of his poor understanding in the general interests of America, but of his defects in sincerity, politeness, and attention to his instructions. Offers him a maxim which may be of use in preventing imaginary hurts.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 229; Bigelow, VI, 124; Smyth, VII, 97).
  - Memorandum., [1778 January.]; A. Mem. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Outline of letters to be written.
  - to [Conrad Alexandre] Gérard [de Rayneval]., 1778 February 1; A. Dr. by Benjamin Franklin of L. 1p.; Benjamin Franklin and Silas Deane. Passy
    Mr. [Arthur] Lee has changed his sentiments regarding Article 12. Owing to the importance of unanimity they suggest that Articles 11 and 12 be omitted in the Treaty of Commerce.
  - to Arthur Lee., 1778 February 1; A. Dr. of L. in Franklin's hand.; Benjamin Franklin and Silas Deane. Passy
    Informing him of their request to M. Gérard [de Rayneval] to omit the 12th Article, although not concurring in his view of it.
    Printed in R. H. Lee's Life of Arthur Lee, Boston, 1829, I, 128.
  - to Prince Mostowski., 1778 February 3; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Will be pleased to receive his visit at the time proposed.
    (In French and English.)
  - to Arthur Lee., 1778 February 15; A. Dr. of L. in Franklin's hand. 1p.; Benjamin Franklin and Silas Deane. Paris
    Two drafts of a letter (only one of which was sent) acquainting Mr. Lee that they are ready to consult with him, whenever he pleases, upon any circumstance relative to the despatches.
  - to Arthur Lee., 1778 February 26; A. Dr. of L. by Dr. Franklin. 2p.; Benjamin Franklin and Silas Deane. Passy
    Necessity of acquainting the Court immediately with the return of their dispatches; Mr. Lee was not consulted as the case seemed a plain one, and any delay dangerous; thinks Mr. Deane deserves his thanks, and neither of them merit his condemnation.
  - to Arthur Lee., 1778 February 28; A. Dr. of L. by Dr. Franklin. 1p.; Benjamin Franklin and Silas Deane. Passy
    The treaties [with France] are being copied in French and English; no desire to postpone Mr. Lee's proposition, only two things cannot be done at once; believe the convoy to have sailed.
  - to William Lee., 1778 March 2; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Should have separated the papers relating to the House of Willing and Morris from those relating to the business of the Committee. Sees no necessity of Franklin being concerned in opening the trunk that contains those papers. If Mr. Lee chooses, on his departure for Germany, he will take care of the trunk [containing the papers of Mr. Thomas Morris] sealed until he receives orders to deliver it up, but otherwise declines to meddle with it.
    Printed in Works (Smith, VII, 115).
  - to William Lee., 1778 March 6; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Returns the keys; wishes Mr. Lee's brother to keep them during his stay in France. Will have no hand in the appointment of his nephew, Mr. [Jonathan] Williams, [Jr.,] as Agent in one of the parts. Did not advise the delivery to himself of the trunk [containing the papers of Mr. Thomas Morris]; said he had no objection to receive it, if Mr. Lee chose to leave it with him sealed.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VII, 116).
  - to Mme. Brillon., [1778.] March 10; A. Dr. of L. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Hailing with delight his lovely confessor; pleads guilty of coveting his neighbor's wife whenever he is with her; asks for instruction in meeting his particular temptation.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Dec., 1906, 311.
  - to Ralph Izard., 1778 March 10; A. Dr. by Benjamin Franklin of L. 1p.; The American Commissioners?, Passy